many people don't realize just how much
we take advantage of the domain name
system or DNS anytime you're converting
from a human readable name like
professormesser.com
and accessing a website there has to be
some conversion to IP addresses and it's
the domain name system that provides
that conversion process DNS is a
hierarchical system which follows a very
specific path to be able to find exactly
the server you're trying to locate and
it's a database that's very distributed
there are many DNS servers around the
world there are over 13 clusters of root
servers at the core of DNS and you often
find generic top-level domains like
a.com or.net and they're also country
code top-level domains for the US Canada
UK and other countries here's an example
of the hierarchy that's used with the
DNS we very often will see a.com address
or dotnet and that's the top-level
domain of this hierarchy underneath com
you might have another domain name such
as professor Messer so you can put
together professormesser.com of course
at professor Messer there may be a web
server and that web servers name may be
www but there may also be a mail dot
professor Messer comm and east dot
professor Messer comm and a West dot
professor Messer calm and you can have
servers that were one level down from
that so there may be an ethan dot West
dot professor Messer calm and so on
visually you can see how this domain
name might work you have a fully
qualified domain name that accompanies
everything within professormesser.com
and within there there may be the
webserver 4ww professor Messer com we
may break out these domains even further
to have a West professormesser.com and
an East dot professormesser.com and
there may be servers that exist in these
different regions and we can specify
they're fully qualified domain name as
Ethan dot West professormesser.com and
Katy East professormesser.com we
mentioned that DNS is a very distributed
database and to be able to find all of
those
different services that are located as
those fully qualified domain names we
may need to ask a number of servers
before we're able to fully resolve their
IP addresses let's start with my laptop
we refer to this device as a resolver
this is a device that will for instance
be trying to find the IP address that
might be associated with the WW
professormesser.com this device is
configured for a local name server that
it will reference this might be a local
server that's within your organization
or it might be a third-party name server
that you're using this resolver will
query that name server to ask where is
the IP address 4ww professormesser.com
the first request we made from the
resolver to the local name server asking
if this particular device knows where WW
professormesser.com happens to be this
local name server does not have this IP
address in its cache so it needs to
start asking other name servers where it
can go to find the WW
professormesser.com IP address its first
step is going to be talking to this root
server the root server is going to
respond back and say if you're looking
for anything with a.com you need to go
to the dot-com name server so the next
step will be the local name server will
talk to the dot-com DNS server this
server will have a list of where my
local DNS server is for
professormesser.com and it will provide
that information to the local name
server the local name server will then
query the professormesser.com name
server which obviously will have the IP
address associated with WW
professormesser.com
and that information is provided to the
local name server at this point the
local name server will let the resolver
know what that IP address happens to be
and it will store that information in a
cache if anyone else that uses this
local name server then needs to access
WWE professormesser.com they can get
that information from the local cache
rather than going through all of these
queries all over again
many organizations will maintain an
internal DNS that's because there are
internal servers that you need to have
some type of reference to
that you may not want to make public on
an external DNS server these internal
DNS azar usually installed and
maintained by your local network team
and it usually is going to have your
internal information that no one else
should have access to it's very common
for example to run a DNS service on a
Windows server so that you are able to
keep up with all of the different
windows devices on your internal private
network if you're an organization that
doesn't need an internal DNS server you
might want to use an external DNS good
example are the ones that are managed by
Google on their Google DNS or quad 9
these external DNS ah's will obviously
not have any information about any
internal devices but you're able to use
and maintain those external resources
without having to run your own server
internally in your organization there's
also a middle ground where you can have
a third party providing you with your
own internal DNS services especially if
you're in a very large environment you
may be having to manage many many
different DNS servers and instead of you
managing that you might want to hand
that off to a third party where you've
outsourced your internal DNS function to
this third party all of these DNS
servers are running in the cloud you
might have multiple instances of them
available around the world and it would
still provide you with the same internal
functionality except you're using a
cloud-based service external to your
organization this also might provide you
with some capabilities you normally
wouldn't have if you were maintaining
your own servers you may have high
availability to have these DNS services
available all the time they may be low
latency servers providing very fast
response time and if you need additional
servers spun up you simply request that
from the third-party DNS and you're able
to scale up and scale down as needed
you