whenever we access a domain name
services server in order to gather
information about the name or the IP
address of a resource we're really
looking through a local database that
has all of these associations between a
fully qualified domain name and an IP
address we call these records on a DNS
server the resource records and it's
really a text file that happens to
contain all of the information we need
to be able to perform these lookups
we'll look at a number of different
record types in this video but there are
over 30 different types that you may
find inside of a DNS server the database
of a DNS server is simply a text file
this is where you would configure the
DNS server and this is where all the
lookups will take place you can see
information in this sample lookup file
that has information about the DNS
server itself and information associated
with the caching you also see mail
exchange records there's records that
are specifying the name in the IP
address of other devices and this lookup
file also contains aliases this allows
us to use different names to associate
to a single fully qualified domain name
one of the most important roles of a DNS
is the one where we are associating an
IP address with a fully qualified domain
name if we look at this section of the
lookup file you'll see there are some
machine names and you'll see IP
addresses associated with those machine
names let's break out these individual
address resource records these address
records are called a records or quad-a
records and they're used to associate
the name with an IP address we use the a
record to associate an IP version 4
address with the name of a device and we
use a quad a record to associate an IP
version 6 address with the name of a
device here's an example of an a record
I have the name WW professormesser.com
there's also a specification of the
class of this record and for most of us
the class of this record will be the
internet class this is an a record so
this will be an IP version 4 address and
you can see the IP version 4 address is
also included as part of this record
that associates this IP address with
Debbie
professormesser.com you can also add a
semicolon at the end of the record to
designate a comment so that you can add
other context to this particular record
there may be times we may want to
associate a number of different names
with an existing device in those
situations you may want to use a
canonical name record or cname record
this is where you would add the alias to
something that already exists for
example if you had a device called mail
my domain name you could also call this
the FTP server for FTP my domain name or
WWE my domain name your DNS server will
recognize that this is a canonical name
it will associate it with the primary
name of this device and then perform the
proper lookup there are also DNS records
that can help you find particular
services on your network for example you
could create a service record or SRV
record that would allow Windows devices
to find Windows domain controllers on
the network or you might add a service
record so that voice-over-ip devices can
find the centralized voice-over-ip
controller on your network for example
here's the service record that's used
for Windows devices to find an active
directory controller you can see the
service is LDAP the protocol name is TCP
domain.com in this example the time to
live is 300 seconds this is the internet
class it is an SRV or service record
there's priority and wait values a port
number and then the target that allows
you to associate this particular service
with a particular device if you're in
charge of the mail servers on your
network then you know the MX record or
the mail exchanger record is an
extremely important record that allows
third parties to be able to find your
local mail servers in your DNS
configuration file the MX record starts
with the I in class for internet it is
an MX record and then you put the name
of the mail server later in the
configuration you'll find the name of
that device is listed with an a record
that will specify the IP address of that
mail server many DNS servers also
contain configuration details for
additional names
servers on the domain these are NS
records or name server records the
format of a name server record would
specify the class of this record which
is Internet this is the name server
record or in s and then you'll list out
the names associated with those name
servers later on in the configuration
you can find a or address records that
will associate the name of the name
server to a specific IP address we
commonly use DNS servers to associate a
name with an IP address but we can also
do the reverse where we provide the name
server with an IP address and it will
provide us with the name it's able to do
this by using pointer records or PTR
records which are effectively the
reverse of an a or a quad a record in
the configuration of our DNS we would
list out the IP addresses associated
with these devices we would specify that
these are PTR or pointer records and
then we would provide the fully
qualified domain name of these devices
another common DNS resource record
you'll find is a txt record or a txt
record this record usually contains
information that will be valuable to
other third party services that are
accessing your DNS for example a text
record might contain SPF protocol
information the stands for sender policy
framework and it's a type of text
message that helps prevent someone else
from spoofing your domain name as emails
are sent out across the internet other
mail servers can check this text record
and determine if this particular email
address really came from your email
server we also use text records to add
DCM information or domainkeys identified
mail this allows your mail servers to
digitally sign outgoing mail and when
the external mail server receives this
they can confirm that this was indeed
digitally signed by your mail server
you're effectively adding your public
key into this particular DNS text record
here's an example of these two text
records in my DNS this first record is
an SPF text record it contains
information that tells other males
servers what the valid mail servers will
be for professormesser.com so I list out
my domain name professormesser.com I've
got a timeout value of 300 seconds this
is a text record and there's the SPF
information third parties will be able
to look at this text record on my DNS
server and see that if mail is coming
from mailgun org then it is authorized
as a mail server for professormesser.com
I also have a domain key text record
listed here which shows the domain key
information for professormesser.com this
is a text value and you can see the
entire public key is listed under this D
CEM one value this allows third party
mail servers that have received a
digitally signed email from my mail
server to get the public key and
validate that signature
you