All of the devices on our
network have their own clock.
This would be every server,
every router, every switch,
every workstation, and
every other device.
There is usually log files,
authentication details,
anything dealing with
logging of information
is all using the date
and time that is gathered
from this clock information.
So, having this synchronized
across all of these devices
is very important.
That would allow you
to compare log files
across multiple devices to
track exactly what's going on
in your environment.
And, of course, you would like
this to occur automatically.
You don't want to have to
go into every single device
and update the clock or have
to update the clock every time
the device is rebooted.
Fortunately, we're able
to do this using NTP--
or the Network Time Protocol.
This allows us to configure
our devices with an NTP server
and then they can check
in to that NTP server
to update their clocks
on a regular basis.
This is an extremely accurate
way of updating these clocks.
Usually, the accuracy is
better than one millisecond
when you're updating
the clocks with an NTP
server on your local network.
If you're configuring
NTP on your network
you may want to have
an internal NTP server.
This is a server
that is in charge
of the clock for all
of the devices that
need to get updates.
And as an NTP server, it
does not modify its own time.
An NTP client is
a device that will
request these times
from the NTP server
and then update their
clocks accordingly.
Sometimes a device can be
both an NTP client and an NTP
server.
So it can update its time
based on the time that
may be available on a
more accurate NTP server
and then it can provide those
updates to other NTP clients
on your network.
If you're planning to configure
this on your network then
you need to decide what devices
will be NTP clients, which
will be NTP servers, and which
devices may be both an NTP
client and an NTP server.
We can associate a
value with an NTP server
that designates how far it is
away from the original time
source.
We call these stratum
layers in NTP.
That's because the
original reference
clock would be stratum 0.
This might be an atomic
clock or a GPS clock
that you've configured.
The next server
away from stratum 0
would be a stratum
1 server, which
is going to be obtaining its
timestamp from a stratum 0
server.
You might also have stratum 2
servers on your network, which
are going to be receiving their
timestamps from a stratum 1
server.
On your client
workstations you generally
would configure your NTP client,
which may specify an IP address
or the domain name of a
particular NTP server.
And if this is inside
of your network
you may want to specify your
own internal IP addresses.
You can also use
multiple NTP servers just
in case one of those
is not available.
If this NTP service is going to
be on your own internal network
you'll need at
least one NTP server
to act as the clock source.
You'll also specify in the
configuration of that NTP
server what stratum this
device happens to be.
So, if a client has the
choice of synchronizing itself
with an NTP server that
has a stratum level of two
and another NTP server that
has a stratum level of one
it will choose to
synchronize itself
with the server that has
the lower stratum number
or the stratum level one.