By far, Ethernet is the most
popular network topology
in the world.
Somebody has a network, and they
have some flavor of Ethernet
that they're using
in their environment.
And there are many
different types
of Ethernet running different
speeds, different types
of cabling, different
types of connector
and different types
of network switches.
In the past, we may have run
ethernet over coaxial cables,
but these days most
modern Ethernet networks
will be using twisted pair
cabling or fiber optic.
If you're running 100 megabit
Ethernet over twisted pair
cables, then you are
using 100BASE-TX.
You'll sometimes
hear this referred
to as fast Ethernet, which is
what we called 100 megabit when
it was released after using 10
megabit Ethernet for so long.
100BASE-TX uses category 5
or better twisted pair copper
cabling, and it uses
two of the pair that
are inside of that cable.
It does not use all four
pair to communicate.
And the maximum
length of a cable
run for the 100BASE-TX standard
is 100 meters in length.
Moving up from 100
megabit Ethernet,
we move into gigabit
Ethernet or 1000 megabit.
The standard for
gigabit Ethernet
that most people are
using is 1000BASE-T.
1000BASE-T gigabit Ethernet runs
over category 5 twisted pair
cable or better.
If you look at the
EIA TIA standard,
you'll see that category
three, four, and five cable
is deprecated.
So usually the minimum
cable that you'll
find available to run for
1000BASE-T is category 5e.
And instead of
using the two pairs
that we used for 100
megabit Ethernet,
our 1000BASE-T gig
Ethernet requires
that we use all four pairs
inside of that twisted pair
of cabling.
If you need to run Ethernet
pass that 100 meter
limitation for copper
cabling, then you'll
probably want to connect
equipment using fiber.
And of course, there are
gigabit Ethernet standards
for fiber optics.
One of these standards
is 1000BASE-SX.
This is gigabit Ethernet running
at 1000 megabits per second
using what's called NIR or
near infrared light bandwidth.
The standard commonly
uses multi-mode fiber
as it's physical medium, so
we can extend this Ethernet
connection generally 220 to
about 500 meters in length
depending on the type of
fiber that we're using.
For much longer
ethernet connections,
you may want to use 1000BASE-LX,
which is gig Ethernet using
a long wave length laser.
You could run 1000BASE-LX
over multi-mode fiber,
and you get about
550 meters in length.
But if you really need
to extend the length up
to five kilometers,
you can use 1000BASE-LX
over single mode fiber.
If you're really looking to
push the throughput of copper
cabling, you can run 10
gig Ethernet over copper
or the 10GBASE-T standard.
This uses frequencies up
to 500 megahertz inside
of this cable, which
is well above what
we use for our gig Ethernet
connections of 125 megahertz.
Because of that,
we will need cable
that's specifically designed
to support these higher
frequencies.
So for 10GBASE-T, you'll be
able to get 55 meters in length.
If you're using cat
6 cable, you can
upgrade to category 6, which
stands for augmented, if you
need to go to 100 meters.
And if you need additional
shielding from interference,
you can choose a
category 7 cable
that is shielding not only
the entire cable itself,
but each individual
pairs of wire.