If you're an early user of
Ethernet over twisted pair
cabling, then you are probably
connecting all of your devices
with a hub.
You'll often hear a hub referred
to as a multi port repeater.
That's because the
operation of a hub
means that any
traffic going into one
of these single ports of
the hub will automatically
be regenerated out of
every other port that
happens to be on that hub.
This makes for a very
simple forwarding mechanism.
If traffic goes into
the hub, it comes out
of the hub on every
other interface.
Since there are no
forwarding decisions
to be made inside
of a hub, we often
say that this is a device
that's operating at OSI layer 1.
Because all devices
are effectively
sharing this network, that
means that you can't really
have a full duplex connection
to any other device
on this network.
All devices connected
to a hub are
going to be running at
half duplex by default.
This also means that if more
devices begin communicating
more often, there will be an
increasing number of collisions
on this half duplex network,
which means the more traffic
increases, the less efficient
this network will be.
If you're using a
gigabit Ethernet network,
then you're not
communicating using a hub.
Hubs are only
available if you're
running 10 megabit Ethernet
or 100 megabit Ethernet.
As you can tell, the
technology behind the hub
is very simplistic.
It's not really designed for
today's high speed networks.
Hubs are no longer manufactured,
and it's even difficult
to find them these days
on the secondary markets.
Imagine if you had a switch
that only had two ports on it.
You had a network on
one side of the switch
and you had a network on the
other side of the switch.
In the early days of networking,
you would have a bridge.
A bridge is making forwarding
decisions in software
based on the MAC
addresses of what
happens to be on both
sides of that bridge.
We would commonly use
these bridges to connect
two separate physical networks.
These networks could be
different typologies.
So we might be connecting
an Ethernet network
to a token ring network by
putting a bridge in the middle.
But we might also
use these bridges
to connect similar typologies.
You could take a very
large Ethernet network
and split it into two
pieces to minimize
the number of collisions
that might be occurring.
Just like today's
modern switches,
these older style bridges
would make forwarding decisions
based on the destination MAC
address inside of a frame.
A good example of
a modern bridge
that would be connecting
different types of networks
would be today's
wireless access points.
You would have a
wireless network
on one side of this access
point and a wired Ethernet
network on the other.
And you're bridging between
these two different typologies.
Our modern switches are an
evolution from the older style
bridges.
Now we have devices with
hundreds of interfaces
on the front, rather than
two or four that you might
have on a traditional bridge.
Also, a traditional bridge was
making all of its forwarding
decisions in software.
On today's switches, we are
making all of these decisions
in the hardware of
these device using
a technology known as ASICs, or
Application Specific Integrated
Circuits.
The forwarding decisions
on our modern switches
are exactly the same as
the forwarding decisions
that were made on the
older style bridges.
We're looking at the
destination MAC address
and we're forwarding the
frame depending on where
that MAC address needs to go.
Our modern switches also have
a number of additional features
available to them.
One good example is
power over Ethernet,
where you could plug in a
device that requires power,
and it can receive
power directly
from your network switch.
Some switches might
also include the option
to enable a routing
functionality within exactly
the same chassis.
We call this functionality
multi-layer switching.
You might hear it referred
to as a Layer 3 switch.
That's because there's a
portion of the switch that
is performing the normal
Layer 2 switching function.
And there's another portion
of the switch that's
able to route between
the different VLANs that
are connected to that switch.
If a device is a
router, then it's
forwarding traffic between
different IP subnets.
And it's making its
forwarding decisions
based on the destination
IP address that
might be in that IP packet.
If it's a switch, then we're
making forwarding decisions
based on a MAC address.
That's why we refer to
routers as Layer 3 devices
and switches as Layer 2 devices.
Routers will often
connect different types
of network typologies.
On one side, you might
have an Ethernet network
running over fiber.
And on the other
side of the router,
it might be a wide area network
that's running over copper.
You generally don't
connect to any network
these days without
a firewall in place.
Firewalls make decisions
about whether traffic
is allowed or not allowed
through the network based
on Layer 4 information.
This might be a TCP
or UDP port number.
Modern firewalls
take that even higher
and can look into the
application that's
going across the network
and make decisions on
whether certain applications
are allowed or not.
We often refer to those
as Layer 7 firewalls,
or next generation firewalls.
Many firewalls also
provide other features.
You could configure your
firewall as a VPN endpoint
at your main location,
and configure
another firewall as a VPN
endpoint at a remote site.
That will allow
you to encrypt all
of the traffic that flows
between the main location
and any of your remote sites.
Some firewalls can be
configured as a proxy.
So they'll stop the
network communication,
make the request on your
behalf, receive the response,
make sure the response is
appropriate for you to receive,
and then send that traffic
down to your workstation.
Many firewalls can also be
configured as a Layer 3 device.
So they can route all
of the traffic going
in and out of the internet.
So not only are they
making security decisions
based on Layer 4 UDP/TCP
port numbers or Layer 7
applications, but
they can also act
as a router to send traffic
between different IP subnets.
In many enterprise
networks, we'd
use wireless access points
to be able to connect people
to a wireless network.
This is a little different
than the wireless
router you might have
in a home office that
has the router, the
switch, the wireless access
point, the firewall, and some
other components within it
as well.
If you were able to pull
out just the wireless piece,
you would have a
wireless access point.
As we mentioned earlier,
a wireless access point
is a Layer 2 device.
It's effectively a bridge
between a wireless network
and an Ethernet network.
Many organizations will deploy
many wireless access points
throughout multiple
floors of a building
so that you can
always be connected
to the wireless network.
The device we call
a modem is named
after the modulator/demodulator
function that is happening
inside of this device.
It's very common to have
modems, for example,
on traditional phone lines.
If devices in two locations
needed to communicate,
they could put a
modem on each side
and communicate over
traditional phone lines.
These phone lines have limited
frequencies that are available,
and therefore, there's a
limited amount of bandwidth
that you could send between
those two locations.
You'll sometimes see modems
used as a secondary, or backup,
system to use the plain old
telephone service or the POTS
system to be able
to communicate when
all other forms of
communication are unavailable.
If you have DSL
in your location,
then you're probably
connecting to the DSL network
using a DSL modem.
If you have broadband internet
from your cable company,
they will provide you
with a cable modem.
Although technically, a cable
modem is more of a bridge
than it is a modem.
Sometimes you just need to
convert between different types
of network media.
You don't need to make
forwarding decisions
based on a Layer 2 MAC address
or a Layer 3 IP address.
You're really just looking
to change communication
from running over a
copper network to a fiber,
and perhaps back again.
In those scenarios, you might
want to use a media converter.
This is a good example
of a media converter.
This operates at OSI Layer 1.
It's simply changing
the physical layer
from a copper network to a
fiber network or vise versa.
You might use one of
these media converters
if you need to extend the
communication over a very
long distance.
We know that Ethernet
can support up
to 100 meters of communication.
But if you need to go
kilometers in distance,
you might want to include a
media converter to convert
to fiber, extended it
over that long distance,
and then, perhaps,
convert it back to copper
on the other end.
You could also
use this if you've
been provided with
fiber connections,
but your switch only
supports copper connections.
You could use the
media converter
to convert from fiber
to copper to provide
that connection to the switch.
This is usually an active
conversion that's taking place.
So these devices very
commonly need to be powered.
You don't generally
see a device that's
converting from fiber to copper
without some type of power
source being connected.
In fact, it's not uncommon to
see rack-based media converters
like this one that have
central power supplies that
provide power to all of these
different media converters.
Our wireless networks
never seem to extend as far
as we would like them to go.
That's because sometimes,
we don't have a choice where
we put an access point.
There might be a single room
where we have an Ethernet
connection, and
that's the only place
available to plug in that
wireless access point.
With a wireless
range extender, you
can increase the size of
that wireless network.
You can think of this as
a wireless repeater that's
able to receive
a wireless signal
and then repeat that
signal to a local area.
Here's how this
wireless range extender
might work in a typical house.
Let's say that your cable modem
connection comes into a family
room, and that's the only
place available to put
a wireless access point.
We'll put it up
high on this shelf.
And it might cover a
certain area of the house.
But you can see that the
kitchen and the master bedroom
don't have any coverage.
So we might install a
wireless range extender
right in the middle, maybe
in this hallway upstairs.
And when we turn that
on, we can extend
that wireless signal to
cover more of this house
just by adding that
single repeater
right in the middle
of the communication.
Remarkably, voice
communication continues
to be something
we use even today.
We are using different ways to
communicate over these voice
type networks by using
voice over IP telephones
or other types of software-based
voice over IP endpoints.
This means we now have options.
We can use voice over
IP instead of using
the traditional plain old
telephone service or POTS
lines.
And we could use different
types of platforms
to be able to send this
voice over IP communication.
We could use a traditional
physical handset,
or we could use software
that's built into a browser,
or on our mobile devices.