A multilayer switch can
provide multiple functions
on a network.
It can act as a switch,
so it can forward
traffic based on MAC addresses.
But it can also act
as a router, which
means it's making forwarding
decisions based on the Layer 3
addresses that are passing
through this device.
This is often a function that
is bundled together and marketed
together as a single device.
It's often referred to
as a Layer 3 switch.
In reality, these two functions
are working independently
inside this individual chassis.
So there might be
switching occurring,
and all occurring at Layer 2.
And a completely different
part of this device
is providing the
router at Layer 3.
We've effectively taken
two different devices--
a switch and a router--
and simply combined them
within the same chassis.
Almost every
organization is going
to have a wireless network.
And it's usually one that
extends everywhere you
might go inside of a
particular facility.
There's usually not a
single access point.
There are usually
many access points
that are deployed in
this organization.
These access points may
extend to multiple buildings,
and they may be
located at locations
that are very far away from
where you happen to be sitting.
If you're managing
the wireless network,
then you also know that changes
are happening all the time.
There are changes to access
policies, security policies,
and the configuration of the
access points themselves.
This wireless
network should also
be seamless for your end users.
They should be able
to simply connect
to the wireless network, use
their normal credentials,
and be able to communicate
to all of the services
they need on your network.
These requirements for
a large organization
are much different than
the wireless networks
we have at home.
That's why, in these
large companies,
you might have a
wireless LAN controller.
This allows you to have
centralized management
of all of your
wireless access points
all from one single console.
We often refer to this as
a single pane of glass.
From this single console, you
can deploy new access points.
You can constantly monitor
your wireless network
and look for any
security concerns that
might be occurring.
You can, of course, make changes
to the configurations of all
of your wireless
access points, and then
provide reports on how much
these wireless access points
are being used and by whom.
These wireless LAN controllers
are often proprietary.
So they're specific to
the brand of access point
that you're using
in your network.
If you're providing some
type of service to end users,
then some of your
biggest concerns
are making sure that your
service remains available
and it remains something
that is responsive
when people try to use it.
One way to provide both
uptime and availability
and an efficiency
with the application
is to implement some
type of load balancing.
Load balancers are often used
for large scale implementations
of web servers,
database servers,
and other major
services on the network.
When we're implementing
these load balancers
for fault tolerance,
we're usually
putting multiple servers
behind the load balancer.
If one server happens to
fail, all of the other servers
are still available to provide
that service to the end user.
This is how we might
configure the load using
these multiple servers.
So we would bring up a server
A, a server B, a server C,
a server D, and we put them
all behind a load balancer.
Your users coming in from the
other parts of the network
are simply connecting
to the load balancer
to be able to use this.
And the load
balancer is deciding
which particular servers will
handle that particular request.
This load balancer is often
monitoring the response
that it's getting
from these servers.
And if one server
begins to slow down,
it can balance the load
across the remaining servers.
The load balancer might also
be providing a TCP offload.
We know if we're communicating
to a device with TCP,
there's the normal three
way TCP handshake that
has to occur for every session.
The load balancer will provide
that TCP handshake to the end
user, but the communication
to the individual servers
behind the load balancer,
we use a session
that's already up and running
and will remain that way.
That removes another level
of overhead from the servers,
and the load balancer manages
all of the TCP handshake
overhead.
SSL encryption can also
provide additional overhead
from the server.
So instead of doing that
encryption and decryption
process on the server,
the load balancer
will manage and be an endpoint
for SSL communication.
Load balancers can
also be configured
to cache client requests.
So if someone makes a request
down to any of these servers,
the load balancer will
cache that information
and provide the
results to that user.
If another user asks for
exactly the same information,
the load balancer will simply
pull that from the cache
and send it back to the
user without ever querying
the servers that are behind it.
Many load balancers will
support multiple protocols.
And it may prioritize certain
protocols over others.
It can also provide
prioritization
at the application level.
So certain applications
on these servers
may have a higher priority
than other applications running
on exactly the same servers.
An IDS or an IPS is an
intrusion detection system
or intrusion prevention system.
These are devices that
we put on our network
to monitor all of the
communication that's going
in and out of our network.
These are specifically
looking for security events.
They're looking
to see if someone
is trying to perform an
exploit against an operating
system or an application, or
someone who might be trying
to perform a buffer overflow
or some type of data injection.
There's two different
flavors of these devices.
The intrusion
detection system is
one that's designed
to alert when there
is these types of problems.
But it doesn't actively
block any traffic
from going through your network.
An intrusion
prevention system is
designed not only to identify
these security issues,
but to also block them
from entering your network.
There are many different
ways that an IDS or an IPS
can identify these
security anomalies.
One way is through a
signature-based match.
This is looking for a
very specific signature.
This happens to be a
signature from an IPS
that is looking for
the configure worm.
It's looking for an exact
match of this information.
And if it finds the
match, it will then
perform the alerting
or blocking function
that you've configured
in your IDS or your IPS.
Many modern IDS or
IPS devices will also
monitor your network
over time and determine
what is normal on your network.
If something happens
that is outside the norm
or is an anomaly, it
will then give you
the option to
either allow or not
allow that traffic
through the network.
These devices can
also be configured
to look for a certain
type of behavior.
If somebody accesses a file
in a certain way, for example,
it may decide to flag that and
allow you to make a decision on
whether that's allowed or not.
And some of these
devices use heuristics,
which are a very
broad description
of malicious activity.
Instead of having a
specific signature,
heuristics are able to use
artificial intelligence
to determine if a
particular traffic
flow seems to be malicious,
and then can take action
based on that.
A proxy is a
security device that
sits in the middle
of the communication
between the users and
the external network
that they're accessing.
The proxy will receive the
request that the users make
and then make that
request on their behalf
to the service that's on
the outside of the network.
It will then receive the
response to that request,
examine it, make sure there's
nothing malicious inside of it,
and then send the response
down to the users.
It's common to use
proxies for URL
filtering and content scanning.
It can also be used
to cache information
to improve the overall
performance of the network
communication.
If your organization is
using an explicit proxy,
then the applications
have to know
how to use that proxy to be able
to communicate to the outside.
And applications have
to be specially written
so that they're able
to take advantage
of this proxy technology.
A more common proxy is
a transparent proxy.
With a transparent
proxy, the applications
don't have to be
written a certain way.
And your users don't even
know the proxy is there.
Your users will simply browse
to the internet as usual,
and the transparent proxy will
intercept that communication.
The proxy then makes the
request on their behalf
and receives the response.
It examines the response,
and if everything looks good,
it provides the response
to the end user.
As you can imagine, a proxy
has to be specifically written
to be able to understand how
certain applications will
operate.
And it's very common for these
application-level proxies
to be able to
understand, perhaps,
one application, such as HTTP.
You may have to enable
additional features
or use additional
proxies if you need
to be able to proxy other types
of applications, such as HTTPS,
FTP, and any other type of app.
A VPN concentrator
is a device we
would install onto
our network that
would allow us to support VPNs,
or Virtual Private Networks.
This would allow someone on
the outside of our network
to communicate over
the public internet,
but send that communication
in encrypted form.
When it's received by
our VPN concentrator,
it's decrypted and then put
onto our local internal network.
This VPN concentrator can
be a standalone device.
But we can also integrate
this into most firewalls.
So the firewall is providing
not only the security gateway
to your network, but it's
also acting as the endpoint
for these VPN tunnels.
For smaller implementations,
you could even
create a VPN concentrator
using software
on an individual server instead
of using dedicated hardware.
You would also need
client software
on the end station that's able
to communicate to these VPN
concentrators.
And often, operating
systems will
ship with certain types of VPN
software built into the OS.
For a remote access VPN,
we'd have a VPN concentrator
at our main location.
And inside our network, we have
all of our corporate resources.
The VPN concentrator is
connected to the internet,
which means you
could be anywhere--
perhaps at a coffee shop--
needing access to
the internal network.
You would start up your VPN
software on your laptop,
and it would build
an encrypted tunnel
into the VPN concentrator.
Anything sent over
this VPN tunnel
would all be encrypted between
your laptop and the VPN
concentrator.
If anyone was listening
in the middle,
they wouldn't be able
to make any sense
of this communication.
The VPN concentrator
is in charge
of decrypting that
information and sending it
into the local network.
Any responses would also be re
encrypted by the concentrator
and sent back to the
user on their laptop.
It's very common these
days to configure
a VPN software to be always on.
So if you're outside
the building,
it recognizes that you're
on an external network.
And if you are on
an external network,
it will automatically
build this tunnel back
to the VPN concentrator.
So always, when you're using
this laptop from wherever
you happen to be, you will be
using a secure channel back
to the central office.
Whenever we're using
resources on our network,
we're constantly needing
to identify ourselves.
We need to identify
ourselves when we sit down
at our computer, when we
connect to a wireless network,
or when we try to access a
resource across the network.
To gain access to
these resources,
we need some way to
validate that we are really
who we say we are.
And in those cases, we would
use a triple-a framework
to provide the authentication,
the authorization,
and the accounting to keep track
of exactly what you've accessed
and when on the network.
The authentication
process is one
that we're very familiar with.
We provide a
username, and then we
provide something
secret, like a password,
to prove that we really
are who we say we are.
Based on that information,
we'll be authorized
to use certain resources
on the network based
on the rights and permissions
associated with our username.
This is also going to keep track
of exactly when I logged on,
when I logged off, and exactly
what information was sent back
and forth over the network.
This triple-a
framework commonly runs
on a triple-a server that's
somewhere in our network.
So we may be a client that's
outside of our network
trying to log in and gain
access through a VPN tunnel.
So we'll hit the
VPN concentrator,
and we'll provide our
username and our password
to gain access.
That request is passed
off to the triple-a server
to check to see if the username
and password are legitimate.
And if they are,
the triple-a server
will approve those
credentials, and we'll
have access to the resources
on the inside of the network.
A very common protocol used
for this triple-a service
is RADIUS.
This stands for Remote
Authentication Dial-in User
Service.
And although the name
has dial-in in the name,
it is one of the most popular
authentication protocols
that's used for much
more than just dial-in.
The RADIUS protocol may be
used to authenticate users
to routers and switches.
It may be used to provide
access to servers.
Maybe this is the
protocol that's
used to gain access
over your VPN tunnels.
And it may be used over
your wireless networks using
a 802.1X.
RADIUS is one of the most
popular authentication
protocols, and
you'll see it used
across a number of different
services and operating systems.
So far, we've talked about
many different components
that you could have
in your network.
Routers, intrusion detection
systems, firewalls, proxies,
VPN concentrators, and more.
But if your environment
is relatively small,
you may be able to combine
all of these functions
into a single security device.
This is called a UTM, or Unified
Threat Management device.
Some people will refer to this
as a web security gateway.
A UTM can be used for
URL filtering or content
inspection.
It may be able to
scan files that
are downloaded for any type of
malware that might be inside.
It may also be able to identify
spam in any emails that
might be downloaded.
If you're connecting
to a wide area network,
some of the wide area network
hardware, such as the CSU/DSU,
may also be integrated
into this same chassis.
This could also provide
Layer 3 routing and even
Layer 2 switching
on certain UTMs.
And, of course, from a
security perspective,
we need firewall functionality
and IDS/IPS functionality
in our UTM.
You might also find UTMs that
are able to provide bandwidth
shaping.
So you can prioritize
certain applications
that are communicating
to the internet.
And if you need a
VPN concentrator,
you can add that function and
all of these other functions
at the same time within the
same chassis with a UTM.
These days, firewalls
are much more
than devices that can allow
or disallow traffic based
on a TCP or UDP port number.
Modern firewalls are able to
look at the applications that
are flowing across the network.
And we call these next
generation firewalls, or NGFW.
You might also see
these next generation
firewalls called
application layer
gateways, stateful multilayer
inspection devices, or devices
that are performing
deep packet inspection.
That's because a next
generation firewall
is looking at every
bit and byte that's
going through the network.
It's looking at
every frame that's
passing through the network, and
making security decisions based
on what happens to be within
all of the data of that frame.
So it may be able to allow
communication to Facebook,
allow communication to Twitter,
but not allow someone to post
to Facebook or post to Twitter.
That's because these firewalls
can really understand
all of the applications in use.
And, in some cases, can
understand different functions
of the applications
you happen to be using.
In most organizations, everyone
has a phone on their desk.
We used to accomplish this
by using a PBX, that's
a Private Branch Exchange.
You effectively have your
own private phone switch
within your company.
That phone switch then connects
to your phone provider network,
and you're able to send
and receive phone calls.
This also meant that we had
to run additional telephone
lines to everyone's desk.
So it would be very common to
run two wires for every desk.
One wire for the
telephone, and another wire
for the local area network.
Today, we're using a
voice over IP PBX, where
we're able to integrate
all of your different voice
over IP devices.
Your voice over IP handsets,
voice over IP software
that's in your mobile
devices and in your browser,
and you're able to
make phone calls
using those devices over your
existing local area network.
With his voice over
IP PBX, you no longer
need to run multiple
cables to every desk.
These devices will simply plug
in to the existing Ethernet
connections.
Of course, not
everything in the world
is communicating using these
voice over IP protocols
and technologies.
So in some cases,
you also need a voice
over IP gateway that can
convert your voice over IP
communication into something
the traditional public switch
telephone network
can understand.
These days, a lot of the
malicious software and data
leakage is occurring within
the data of our applications.
So to control that, we
may want to implement
some type of content
filtering on our network.
This would allow us to look into
the data going back and forth
and determine if somebody
may be transferring
sensitive information into
or out of our network.
This can also look for
inappropriate content.
If we wanted to provide parental
controls on our network,
we would commonly
use a content filter.
And, of course, we need to
be able to look for malware.
So usually anti-malware
and anti-virus
is built in to the
content filtering system
we might have on our network.