Virtualization has drastically
changed to our modern data
centers.
We used to have
data centers that
may have 100 individual
servers in them,
and of course, all of
those individual servers
were all connected together
with enterprise switches
and we connected all
of the separate VLANs
together with
enterprise routers.
And of course, there
was redundancy,
so we always had multiple
switches and multiple
routers to ensure there was
up time to these services.
And then we virtualized
the data center.
We removed those
100 physical devices
and created them all
virtually within one
single large physical system.
So now that all of
these servers are
living in this
virtual world, how
do we provide switching
and routing services
for all of those networks
and all of those VLANs?
Of course, all of those
hundreds of servers
that are now
virtualized will still
need to be able to communicate
to the physical world.
The component that
provides this link
between the virtual world
and the physical world
is the hypervisor.
You might also hear
this referred to
as the Virtual Machine Manager.
This is the component
that manages
the entire virtual platform for
all of those virtual servers.
If you're running a virtual
machine on your existing
desktop, you may want to be sure
that the hypervisor is using
a CPU that could
support virtualization
within the hardware of the CPU.
Intel calls this VT for
virtualization technology,
and AMD calls it AMDV
for the virtualization.
This hypervisor is the component
in this virtual system that
is maintaining all
of these virtual CPUs
to all of these devices.
It's allowing you to set up
separate networking components,
and it can provide security for
all of these virtual machines.
There are a lot of different
options for networking
when you get into
the virtual world.
A lot of these
hypervisors will have
their own internal
network, so they
can communicate to
all of the local VMs
without ever using
an external network.
You could also use
a shared address
to communicate outside
of the virtual machine.
So there might be
a single Ethernet
card on this virtual
machine platform
and the hundreds of VMs that
are inside of this device
will use that single
IP address associated
with that interface
as the connection
to the outside world.
This effectively is performing
a network address translation
function to be able to use and
share that single IP address.
You can also configure
a virtual machine
to have its own IP address
rather than sharing
a single natted address.
This would be a bridged
network address,
and it will allow the VM to
have its own unique addressing.
And some virtual machines
can be configured
with a private address that
doesn't communicate to anyone.
This is very common
to do if you're
setting up a virtual machine
in a test environment.
But now that all
of these servers
have been put into a
virtual environment,
we can also build out
switches and routers
in this virtual
environment as well.
In this scenario,
I've got a dotted line
around this virtual
world that we've
created with these hundreds of
different servers inside of it.
And of course, there is a
link to the outside world
that eventually will connect
to a physical switch.
Inside of this virtual
world, I built out
a couple of virtual
switches that
are connecting to
these virtual servers,
and I've also got
a virtual router
that's able to route between
these different networks.
Because this is a
virtual environment,
I can make changes
at any time just
by making a few mouse clicks.
These virtual switches
and virtual routers
are all software that's running
in this virtual environment.
So if I'd like to put a back
end process for this server that
happens to have a
separate database server,
I can simply add a
different virtual switch
and now I've got a
way for this server
to communicate on the back
end to a separate database.
Just as I've added virtual
networking components,
I can also add virtual
security components.
I could add a virtual firewall.
So I can have a
firewall protecting
all of the data that's going in
and out of this virtual world.
I can also bring the
security down to a port level
and add multiple
virtual firewalls,
so I'm able to have a
very specific security
policy for every
single link that's
going in and out of every server
in this virtual environment.
There are certainly
advantages and disadvantages
to all of these
different configurations.
But when you're working
with a virtual environment,
you have the flexibility to
build the environment exactly
with the resources and
requirements that you need.